Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's Daf דף daf is Daf
Vav דף ו, daf vav, six and we pick up with the
very bottom of Amud Bet עמוד ב. amud bet. I yes we
dealt with yesterday whole series of issues about lowering the beam and
raising the floor, but I'm just remind because these are going to
be recurring themes the basic issues that came up relating to the
beam, the Kora קורה kora was whether it functioned as a Heker
היכר, heker, as something noticeable or whether it function and its primary
purpose was to be something as a sign or whether its primary
purpose was to serve as a Mechitza מחיצה, mechitza, as a type
of a wall.
So that was one issue. Just by the way to make a
mention of that, if you look at the small little Tosafos Arba
Amos תוספות ארבע אמות Tosafos Arba Amos on He amud bet ה
עמוד ב, He amud bet, if you remember one of the points
was when the Lechi לחי lechi was too wide, it
stopped being a Lechi לחי, lechi, the vertical post, it stopped being
a Lechi לחי lechi and required another Lechi לחי, lechi, it was
quite ironic but when it wasn't specifically put there as a Lechi
לחי, lechi, Tosafos תוספות Tosafos makes an interesting point. He says Afilu
man de'amar lechi mishum mechitza אפילו מאן דאמר לחי משום מחיצה. afilu
man de'amar lechi mishum mechitza. One minute, the same way we had
a question whether the beam, the Kora קורה kora is because of
a Mechitza מחיצה mechitza or Heker היכר, heker, the same is true
about the Lechi לחי, lechi, the vertical post. Is that serving as
a Heker היכר, heker, it's a sign, or is it serving as
a wall? So Tosafos תוספות Tosafos says if it's serving as a
wall, so the longer it is the better, how could it ever
stop being a Lechi לחי? lechi? So he says De'havi lei lo-havu
yoter mi-stasmo
דהוה ליה לאהדורי יותר משתמא, de'havi lei lo-havu yoter mi-stasmo, it should
have helped more. Mikol makom heker kzat bayinan מכל מקום היכר קצת
בעינן, mikol makom heker kzat bayinan, you also need it to be
a little bit of a Heker היכר. heker. So the point being
that as with many things in life these issues are not totally
black and white. It might be primarily about a Mechitza מחיצה mechitza
but a little aspect of a Heker היכר, heker, primarily about a
Heker היכר heker but a little bit. But this is the question
about Lechi לחי lechi and Kora קורה kora whether their primary identity
is that as Mechitza מחיצה mechitza to create like a virtual wall
or as a Heker היכר heker as a sign. That was one
issue we dealt with yesterday and the other issue we dealt with
yesterday was the minimum size of a Maboi מבוי maboi to be
allowed for carrying and allowed for these Rabbinic rules. And the question
was, was the minimum length of a Maboi מבוי maboi Arba Tefachim
ארבעה טפחים arba tefachim which is quite small or Arba Amos ארבע
אמות arba amos and it was argued back and forth. Okay, we
now pick up with the bottom of He amud bet ה עמוד
ב. He amud bet. Two lines from the bottom, last word on
the line. Amar Rav Chana bar Rava amar Rav אמר רב חנא
בר רבא אמר רב, amar Rav Chana bar Rava amar Rav, so
Rav Chana bar Rava says in the name of Rav, Maboi shenifratz
mitzido be-eser מבוי שנפרץ מצדו בעשר. maboi shenifratz mitzido be-eser. So we
had discussed this already yesterday in more than one context. If you
have a break in the wall of the Maboi מבוי, maboi, if
it's on the side, you can tolerate a break up till Eser
Amot עשר אמות. eser amot. First of all, let's remind ourselves that
the door of a Maboi מבוי maboi can be up till Eser
Amot עשר אמות, eser amot, so the front, so we know that
Eser Amot עשר אמות eser amot normally is considered to be not
necessarily
a break but more of an opening. And therefore that's on the
one hand, so we've already seen that idea of Eser Amot עשר
אמות. eser amot. Number two, you might remember yesterday as well we
taught this idea that if the side wall of the Maboi מבוי
maboi breaks and there's a Arba Tefach ארבעה טפחים arba tefach wall
right by the front, then it can tolerate up to a Eser
Ama עשר אמה eser ama gap, right? Remember that we had that?
Right, we have this was your Maboi מבוי maboi and then a
wall broke over here,
so as long as this was Arba Tefachim ארבעה טפחים, arba tefachim,
it could tolerate up to a Eser Ama עשר אמה eser ama
gap over here.
Okay, and that's right, let's just talk about that. Okay, so that's
the first point, that if it's broken on the side up to
Eser עשר, eser, it is not considered that it destroys the wall,
that's a tolerable gap, it's considered almost as an opening.
But Me-rosho be-arba מראשי בארבע me-rosho be-arba if it's at the head
of it however, then it's only four. Now four is always tricky,
all these things are tricky, Tefachim טפחים tefachim or Amos אמות, amot,
but here actually it means Tefachim טפחים, tefachim, a very tiny little
gap. So if it's at the head, only Arba Tefachim ארבעה טפחים.
arba tefachim. Now what do you mean if it's at the head?
The head doesn't have any wall. So what are you talking about?
So Rashi רשי Rashi says the scenario is that the opening was
more than Eser Amot עשר אמות, eser amot, so you had to
build a wall here to make this an acceptable opening. So even
at the head part of it is walled off. Okay, and here
if you have a gap even as small as Arba Tefachim ארבעה
טפחים, arba tefachim,
even if you have a little gap Arba Tefachim ארבעה טפחים, arba
tefachim, then that would could break up this wall and it would
not close off enough of the gap in front. You have to
close it off so it's only a Eser Ama עשר אמה eser
ama opening and this wall that closes it up cannot tolerate a
gap bigger than Arba Tefachim ארבעה טפחים. arba tefachim. So that's a
little bit of a question: why such a tiny gap number one?
And number two: why is it different than the one on the
side? So let's take a look. what the גמרא Gemara says, okay?
I will tell you by the way, let me just, okay, let's
just see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי שנא מצדו בעשר? Mai
shna mitzido b'eser? Why on the side are you allowed a gap
as big as ten אמות, amot, דאמר פתחא הוא, d'amar pitcha hu,
because you say that's not really a break, it's an opening. So
מרישא נמי נימא פתחא הוא? mei'rosha nami neima pitcha hu? Say the
same when there's a little opening, when there's a gap by the
front, that's an opening, and why should it destroy the concept of
the wall, why is it any worse once it's in the front?
So very good question. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav
Huna breih d'Rav Yehoshua, כגון שנפרץ בקרן זוית, k'gon shenifratz b'keren zavit,
דפתחא בקרן זוית לא עבדי אינש. d'pitcha b'keren zavit lo avdi inish.
So he makes it into a special case. He says, you know
what, you're right. Really in the front it could tolerate a bigger
gap. How big, I'll hold off on right now, not as big
as ten אמות, amot, but it really could. Why such a small
one a problem? Because remember just like a scenario we had yesterday,
it's not right over there. It's an opening at the corner. So
this, a corner is not where people put their doors. People put
them, you know, directly at the walls. They don't make a gap
at the corner. So that type of a gap is not considered
to be
an opening, it's considered to be a break. And that's the problem
when it's specifically in the corner. Again, you might remember we had
the same idea
yesterday, yesterday talked about the מבוי's mavoy opening into the חצר's chatzer
opening into the מבוי mavoy at the corners. Here what it's saying
is that a corner, a break at the corner is worse.
You get up to four טפחים tefachim on either side, right?
Yeah, yes, correct. Okay? And presumably because less than four טפחים, tefachim,
you know, it's considered more continuous. Now of course then really you
should want to be less than three טפחים, tefachim, which is really
לבוד, lavud, but again there's a certain degree of a tolerance where,
you know, it's so trivial it's not even considered to be a
break at all. Okay? You don't need continuous wall, you just need,
you know, not to be considered that there's a break in the
wall. So a small amount is not a problem, but once it's
four טפחים tefachim and it's significant, and since you can't consider it
a door at the corner, then it's considered a break clearly.
So I presume this is talking about right angle corners, but then
there are obtuse angle corners and then things that are barely a
corner at all.
Right. So, yeah, you mean if, you mean if in the beginning,
if the whole מבוי mavoy and the חצר chatzer was already sort
of structured something like this, yeah, like that, would a break here
be as considered as much of a non-doorway break? Yeah, I don't
know the answer to that. I don't know what, you know, at
what stage, I mean, it's considered to be a, yeah, I don't
know the answer to that. Good question. Yes, Mike.
Is this in the case where you already have to have your
קורה korah because it's wider than ten אמות? amot?
No, you always need a קורה korah at the opening of the
מבוי. mavoy.
No, but like you said so no matter how big, even if
that wall was like 50 feet long?
No, no, no, that's true if, you know, if you had a
complete wall you wouldn't, but assuming you've got an opening, you know,
it's then but it's not because it's wider than ten אמות, amot,
you made it less than ten אמות amot which allowed you to
have a קורה. korah. Okay? Say again, what did you? If it's
wider than ten אמות, amot, the opening is wider than ten אמות,
amot, then a קורה korah doesn't work. Okay? So it's less than
ten אמות amot and you need a קורה, korah, but anyway but
the problem there is is that that's not, that's considered a break.
All right, so that's his position. Now what if there actually was
a break in the really front of the wall, what would that
be, we don't know exactly, I'll get back to that in a
minute, but let's first see the opposite opinion, or the opposing opinion
I should say.
Okay, רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna amar, so that's what רב חנן
בר רבא Rav Chanan bar Rava says in the name of רב,
Rav, but רב הונא Rav Huna says אחד זה ואחד זה בארבע.
echad zeh v'echad zeh b'arba.
Even a side break is only four טפחים. tefachim. We mentioned this
yesterday as well, remember we said that like in a חצר chatzer
a side break, a break is ten. In a מבוי mavoy a
break is four. And everybody said what do you mean, you said
ten, I said yeah I know I know but we're going to
see another opinion that's four. Well here's the other opinion, I don't
know if you remember that from yesterday, it's hard to keep all
this in your head, but anyway we did have this yesterday, and
here we see this opinion, I might have said yesterday four אמות,
amot, but anyway it gets confusing even for me, but anyway but
here
the position it's very clear that there's a position that even at
the side it can only tolerate a four טפח tefach break. Now
that's tiny, right? And what about the things we said yesterday, we
said you could have a whole big up to ten אמות, amot,
right? If people remember. So, so what is this only four טפחים
tefachim by the side? So let's take a look. וכן אמר ליה
רב הונא לרב חנן בר רבא, V'chen amar leh Rav Huna l'Rav
Chanan bar Rava, similarly said רב הונא Rav Huna to רב חנן
בר רבא, Rav Chanan bar Rava, לא תיפל גלאי, lo tiphal galai,
don't disagree with me, that you know my position that four טפחים
tefachim is already a problem on the side. Why? דרב איקלע לדמחריא,
deRav ikla l'Demacharya, רב Rav came to this place Macharya, and your
whole position, רב חנן בר רבא's Rav Chanan bar Rava idea of
ten אמות amot on the side was said in the name of
רב. Rav. He says listen I want to tell you what happened.
רב Rav came to this place called Chamarya ועבד עובדא כוותי v'avid
uvda k'vati
and he did the act like me. He basically invalidated a מבוי
mavoy with a break that was four טפחים. tefachim. You know,
so clearly, how can you say in the name of רב Rav
that he allows a ten אמה amah break in the side of
a wall? So אמר ליה, ama lei, אמר ליה ama lei he
said back to him, רב בקעה מצא וגדר בה גדר. Rav bika
matza ve-gadar ba-geder. So this is a nice little sort of I
don't know if you could say play on words, play on metaphor,
okay,
it literally means רב Rav found a wide open field and made
a fence around it, made a wall around it. And what that
is an image for, it's a metaphor used to say that he
was, you know, it's like very much we sometimes say that what's
the, the enterprise of the rabbis is they make גדרים, gedarim, right?
They make fences around the law. So here what it's saying is
that it's a theme we saw before that even if the law
might allow something, sometimes the rabbis felt that because the people were
not so knowledgeable or scrupulous, they had to actually be stricter than
the law really demanded so would not lead to sin. So sometimes
a way of articulating that, expressing that is he found a wide
open space, meaning like lack of appropriate boundaries, people would not, you
know sort of keep, you know, were not being as scrupulous or
didn't have the knowledge they needed to keep within the bounds, so
he had to make a fence in order to protect the law.
He had to make he had to make a wall, he had
to make a fence. So that's his basic answer is is that
רב Rav gave this ruling and he invalidated the מבוי mavoy with
a smaller break because he thought that the he because he thought
that the people, you know, that that he needed to be stricter
because of the lack of care and scrupulousness in this place. Obviously
it's a play on words because we're talking about breaks in a
wall and here what he's saying is is that really we could
tolerate a bigger break, but רב Rav had to make a more
of a wall, demand more of a wall where a break could
be tolerated because of the realities of this place. Yes, רבקה. Rifka.
Why is why is this attitude that people are more likely to
obey if you are stricter? Why not make give them more latitude
and then say then they're more likely to obey if we make
it easy? If we make it hard, they're going to ignore it?
Well, you are right that that that that, you know, I think
a lot of it has to do with where you think, you
know, why you think why you think there's the lack of observance.
You know, is lack of observance a certain field like sense like
things are too constrained and you have to you need you know
need more, you know, you need more autonomy or freedom, and then
you could say if you make things more constrictive it leads to
even greater, you know,
desire to express freedom and and to go against those norms. But
if the issue is more just like let's say sloppiness, you know,
that so you don't so that's so if you tell people this,
they'll be a little sloppy and they'll, you know, and they'll allow
something that's a little bit more than that. So therefore so if
it's about sloppiness, so you allow less so even with the sloppiness,
they haven't crossed the line. That I think is the logic. Okay,
but I think you're right. I think it's different when it gets
to an issue of a greater degree to express freedom or autonomy
and so on, that, you know, that might be the whole debate
of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel ve-Beit Shammai along those types
of lines. I think that that's correct. Alright, so that's his answer.
רב Rav basically says ten אמה, amah, that was a special case.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, let's go on. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק כוותיה דרב הונא מסתברא. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak kevasei
de-Rav Huna mistabra. It makes sense like רב הונא Rav Huna that
it's only four טפחים. tefachim. Again, pretty shocking because yesterday we taught
you could have a ten אמה amah break which we'll get back
to. But he says I think רב הונא Rav Huna makes sense.
Why? דאיתמר, De-itmar, because it was taught. מבוי עקום, Mavoy akum, let's
say you have a bent מבוי. mavoy. You have a picture there
in רש"י, Rashi, it's very it's simple. Simply you have a מבוי
mavoy that is at a right angle. Now remember basically the way
it works is, right, you have your houses
opening into a חצר, chatzer, right,
a yard. You have your חצרות chatzers opening into a מבוי, mavoy,
which is an alley,
and you have your מבואות mavoys opening up into the רשות הרבים,
reshut ha-rabim, right?
So if anybody's ever been in suburbia, you know, this is the
way it works, right? You have your main streets, you go to
side street and then you go off into one of the courtyards.
Okay, that's basically the way it works. Okay, so that's how it
would work. And sometimes your מבואות, mavoys, right, sometimes your side streets
would go all the way through into the other main street.
Right, and then your houses would sort of be in the yards
of the houses would be around like that. So that's a normal
type of a configuration. A
מבוי מפולש, mavoy mefulash, straight through, or a מבוי סתום, mavoy satum,
where it where it dead ends. But we are now talking that
you have a a
מבוי mavoy that right angles, okay, and here is the next רשות
הרבים. reshut ha-rabim.
So the question is in this type of a case,
how does it work? Do you need, you know, if you had
a straight through מבוי, mavoy, then you couldn't use the לחי. lechi.
the קורה, kora, because לחי lechi or קורה kora assumes three full
walls, okay? If you had a dead-end one and it had three
walls, you could use לחי lechi or קורה. kora. Here, what is
it like? On the one hand you could say it's like it
has three walls, if you just stop here, it sort of has
these houses here as a wall, right? And then if you stop
here it's sort of dead-end. Or do you say it's like it
goes straight through and it only has two walls? So how do
you treat a
right-angle מבוי mavoi for allowing you to use a לחי lechi or
קורה? kora? Two walls. Invisible walls. Let's take a look. So דאתמר
de-itmar and all of this is going to work back to the
discussion of whether it's a four טפח tefach break or a ten
אמה ama break. Okay. דאתמר, de-itmar, it was said:
מבוי עקום, mavoi akom, a bent מבוי. mavoi. רב אמר, Rav amar,
תורתו כמפולש. toraso kemefulash. It is like a, it's like a
open-ended מבוי, mavoi, like a straight-through side street and therefore you need
a, you cannot make a, there's nothing you can do, you cannot
make, I mean maybe there is but it's drastic. Okay, but you
certainly cannot satisfy, we'll talk about it, certainly you cannot be satisfied
with a לחי lechi or קורה. kora. ושמואל אמר, Veshmual amar, תורתו
כסתום. toraso kesatum. And שמואל Shmuel says it's like each one is
like a dead-end one and therefore it's accept... and therefore you can
make a לחי lechi or קורה. kora. Now by the way, רש"י
Rashi has two opinions. One opinion is you just do your לחי
lechi or קורה kora here and you're done and each one of
these is like a dead-end in its local place. Okay. That's... and
then רש"י Rashi has another opinion which says no, no, no, here
also you need some type of a thing. Okay, to sort of
what? Well, it sort of serves as, it's questionable for both because
it sort of serves as both because you know this one goes
this way so you're seeing, you know, there's one, you imagine, you
don't have to imagine two, you know, you can imagine this is
one מבוי, mavoi, this is the other, and this is the opening.
You don't need to do one over there.
Right, correct. You don't need to... Yes. You also need to do
it on
the other ends at the very end. What? Where you put it
for your שיתוף. shituf. No, because this is my מבוי mavoi here,
then when I turn into that מבוי mavoi I have that side
of this is it then when I go into that one, you...
one is enough, you won't need two. Okay, רש"י Rashi says only
one. Anyway, so that's the debate. So במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what
are we talking about? אילימא ביותר מעשר. Eleima beyoser me-eser.
If the width of the... if the width of the of the
מבויים mavoys is more than ten, then בהלין לשמואל תורתו כסתום? behalin
lishmuel toraso kesatum? How could שמואל Shmuel say that it's like it
is sealed? Meaning look, one minute. You've got this gap here on
the side of the מבוי, mavoi, right? This מבוי, mavoi, this one
have got this gap which is the opening of the other מבוי.
mavoi. So that's essentially a break, a break in the wall, right?
So if this gap is bigger than ten אמות, amot, how could
you even begin to consider this sealed? Right, even forget that מבוי,
mavoi, it has too big of a gap there. Is that clear?
Okay. So even just if you completely forget there's two problems. One
is if you keep on going down the street you'll hit רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim. The other problem is you got a break in
the wall, forgetting that. So it says if this is bigger than
ten, nobody could say it's like it's sealed. So אלא לאו, ella
lav, you must say בעשר, be-eser, that the width of the מבוי
mavoi is less than ten, ten or less, and therefore it's possible
to say you look at it as each one as if it's
sealed. The break isn't a problem, the fact that if you continue
going you'll get into רשות הרבים reshus harabim is also not a
problem. Okay, so that's a pretty good argument that we're talking that
these מבויים mavoys are less than
ten. דקאמר רב, Decamar Rav, תורתו כמפולש. toraso kemefulash. But you see
that רב Rav says, and now we're discussing the position of רב,
Rav, that it is considered to be an open-ended מבוי. mavoi. So
if רב Rav really held that... if רב Rav really held that
what do you call it, that a break, you could tolerate a
break... you know anything less than ten you could tolerate a break...
there could be no... why would רב Rav say that this is
considered an open-ended מבוי? mavoi? There's an obvious answer to that, right?
Here again, it's a simple question. Look. שמואל Shmuel said each מבוי
mavoi is like its separate, it's like a dead-end. The only thing
we have to deal with is how big is the break. The
break has to be less than ten. Nobody says a break more
than ten can be tolerated. Okay, so the break is less than
ten. So now the גמרא Gemara says if the break is less
than ten, why does רב Rav say... why would רב Rav call
this an open-ended מבוי? mavoi? I mean why shouldn't we be able
to tolerate the break if רב Rav allows for breaks less than
ten? But there's an obvious... because it goes through to the רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim. Because it goes into the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
It's not a normal break, it's a break that feeds into the
רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay, which is what the גמרא Gemara answers.
You can't prove from there that רב Rav generally, you know, cannot
tolerate breaks less than ten. The גמרא Gemara says אלמא פרצת מבוי
מצדו בארבע. alma pirtzas mavoi mitzido be-arba. You see a break of
the מבוי mavoi in the side
is only, you know, even less than ten is a problem, even
with being four. You see רב Rav holds four, or else why
is this a
problem? So the
גמרא Gemara says רב חנא בר אבא Rav Chana bar Abba will
tell you
no, שאני התם דקא בקי רבים. shani hasam dekabaki rabim. That's different
because the רבים... rabim... A little break so sometimes it's used it
doesn't maybe it needs to be ten to be a problem. Here,
it's a major thoroughfare people are going from one מבוי maboy to
the other they're crossing through and we could all have this in
suburbia too this would be a good shortcut right? If you had
to they start putting speed bumps along the way so you don't
use the shortcut. So he says that makes that break a problem
but normally a break less than ten might not be a problem.
And they're almost saying that this is just an extension of the
רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim and we're going to get to that in a minute
when does that side street especially when it is a real open-ended
side street become a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim as well. Okay? So
so that so the גמרא Gemara says so you can't prove it
from there. Now the גמרא Gemara asks a question in the opposite
that we've been saying all along that the issue is ten אמות.
ammos. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
מכלל miklal does that mean to suggest דרב הונא סבר אף על
גב דלא קא בקעי בה רבים de-Rav Huna savar af al gav
de-lo ka baki bah rabbim that when we say there's a debate
whether it's a ten אמות ammos or four טפחים tphachim the one
that says even four טפחים tphachim is a problem would say even
if it's not a major thoroughfare even if the masses are not
bursting through it that even a you know in any normal מבוי
maboy a little break is a problem? How could you say that?
מאי שנא מדרב אמי ורב אסי? mai shna me-de-Rav Ami ve-Rav Assi?
How is it different from רב אמי Rav Ami and רב אסי?
Rav Assi? You will all remember yesterday that רב אמי Rav Ami
and רב אסי Rav Assi said that we started I mentioned this
at the beginning of the day that when you have a break
by the front of the מבוי maboy right they were the ones
that said it's basically this picture that I was drawing it the
other way if you have a break here as long as this
is four טפחים tphachim you can tolerate a break up to ten
אמות ammos right? We taught that yesterday. So the question is so
look everybody says that ten אמות ammos is okay. What's the logic
of the position that says you know that says even more than
four טפחים tphachim is a problem? We allow up to ten אמות.
ammos. Okay? And so the גמרא Gemara says no שאני התם shani
hatam where am I? רב Rav התם דאיכא גדודי הכא דליכא גדודי.
hatam de-ika gedudey hacha de-leka gedudey. There it said there
there would be גדודי. gedudey. גדודי gedudey would be some of the
foundation of the original wall because remember the wall had been built
it wasn't it didn't start with an opening. The wall had been
built and then it got knocked down right? So it broke. So
in that case if you've got you know I mean if this
is the side view of where you have your break so you
know this is the wall that had the break and and we
say we can tolerate up to ten אמות amos of a break
that's when there is some basically foundation that is still left here.
So there's some foundation that prevents it from that sort of makes
it more of a continuity and also prevents from ease of people
just using it and going through it so it seems so it
is less of a break. When do we say when do they
say that four טפחים tphachim is a problem if there is absolutely
no foundation? Okay so a lot of things to consider I'll try
to pull it all together. When you have a break in the
side of the wall of a מבוי maboy how big of a
break is a problem? Yesterday we said ten אמות amot which makes
a lot of sense because of the idea of what do you
call it of the that you know up to ten אמות amos
it could be considered an opening. Today we find that it is
a major debate. That there's one opinion that says ten אמות amos
always like we taught yesterday and another's the opposite extreme even four
טפחים. tphachim. Anything that is even of minimum significance. How do you
deal each one has an exception? Even the one that says four
טפחים tphachim will admit that if some foundation is left then it
could be up to ten אמות. amos. Even the one that says
ten אמות amos might say that if it's a thoroughfare that goes
straight to another רשות הרבים reshus harabbim then that could then that
could be a problem. But under normal circumstances no foundation and no
leading straight into another רשות הרבים reshus harabbim you have a major
debate between whether you can allow a break up to ten אמות
amos which is huge or anything more than four טפחים. tphachim. Now
again four טפחים tphachim sounds radical and I would tell you that
a piece of information you're missing here that the גמרא Gemara introduces
later is that and רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos already start discussing
is that part of the problem with a break is not just
lack of continuity but the fact that then it becomes an alternative
entrance and exit. And therefore if the whole idea of the לחי
lechi or the קורה korah of one of the ideas let's say
is to be a היכר heker and to serve that the idea
is that you need some type of a לחי lechi or קורה
korah by the entrance and exit then maybe if you have a
break once it's four טפחים tphachim it's big enough to serve as
an entrance or exit then that could create the problem. Not so
much because it creates because you're saying you don't have enough wall
here but because now you don't have just one entrance and exit
and and our הלכה halacha requires a לחי lechi or קורה korah
by the entrance or exit this creates another one. Okay so that
is the debate of ten אמות amot or four טפחים tphachim major
debate about how big the size of the break in the side
of the wall could be. In terms of the special case of
when you have a wall in the front... as well, we also
said that there everybody would agree that a break at the corner
is a problem because nobody makes an entrance or an exit at
the corner.
We're going to talk more about צורת הפתח? tzurat hapetach?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's a big מסכת. masechet. Okay. Alright.
But he just mentions here because צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. I know.
Yes. Okay. So now we go on in the גמרא. Gemara. Now
I should say that now we actually switch gears and this is
a very important next move in the גמרא. Gemara. First of all,
it'll be more fun, it'll be very relevant, and it's interesting, it
appears here on דף ו daf vav and in שבת Shabbat we
have a almost not the same סוגיא sugya but a highly linked
סוגיא sugya that also appears on דף ו. daf vav. Is there
still a גמרא שבת Gemara Shabbat around? I did want to read
just one line. No, nobody still has a גמרא שבת Gemara Shabbat
here? Okay, we did too good of a job cleaning up. Anyway,
so the גמרא שבת, Gemara Shabbat, you have it? Yeah, I don't
know if it's the right volume.
I don't know if it's the right volume.
This is part two.
No, part two. Okay, anyway. This is part one. Part one. יישר
כח. yasher koach. So the גמרא שבת Gemara Shabbat on דף ו
daf vav
says the following.
So important. תנו רבנן ארבע רשויות לשבת. Tanu Rabbanan arba reshuyot l'Shabbat.
Four domains for שבת. Shabbat. Because what we're about to get into
is a discussion of how do you make an ערוב, eruv, what
we call an ערוב eruv around a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. You
know, or how do you, you know? So first we have to
understand what is defined as a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So ארבע
רשויות לשבת רשות היחיד ורשות הרבים כרמלית ומקום פטור. Arba reshuyot l'Shabbat
reshut hayachid v'reshut harabim karmelit u'makom patur. So it says what's רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid that's relevant for us, and then איזהו רשות הרבים
סרטיא ופלטיא. eizehu reshut harabim stratia u'platya. So סרטיא stratia is a
major street, and a פלטיא platya is like a major square, a
gathering square גדולה, gedola, ומבואות המפולשין זוהי רשות הרבים. u'mevo'ot hamfulashin zohi
reshut harabim. That's how you said it Paula, right? Remember a מבוי
מפולש? mavoi mefulash? So if you have also
back to our more standard
scenario
of, you know, of
side streets linking with, sort of like the layout of Manhattan, although
they would have courtyards, okay, but side streets linking with, you know,
major streets here, this is a מבוי מפולש. mavoi mefulash. So here
are your major streets, that's a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, and the
side streets that directly connect to the major streets on both ends
are also רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, partly because they're used as major
thoroughfares, right, they're major, you know, because of the travel and also
because they don't have three walls, they only have two walls and
therefore those are that's a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Now with that
information, let's turn to our גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן
כיצד מערבין דרך רשות הרבים. Tanu Rabbanan keitzad m'arvin derech reshut harabim.
How do you make an ערוב eruv around a רשות הרבים? reshut
harabim? Now I need to stop here and talk about the terminology
because it's a big, you know, I keep on saying that what
we call an ערוב, eruv, you know when we make like the
wires and the things on the telephone poles, that's not an ערוב.
eruv. That's a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. That's making walls around the
space. The ערוב eruv is when you all join in together for
a box of מצה matzah once you have it defined as a
private domain, that then you have to join together for like a
loaf of bread to allow for carrying in it, to make it
like one domain. So here it uses the term how are you
מערב m'arev a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, which sounds like our terminology.
How do you make an ערוב eruv around רשות הרבים? reshut harabim?
But what it means is what do you have to do to
allow you to make an ערוב eruv around רשות הרבים? reshut harabim?
How do you create the walls so that then you can make
the ערוב, eruv, then you can join together in the, in the,
in the, you know, in the loaf of bread? But that's how
one terminology turns into the other. Because how do you make an
ערוב, eruv, the ערוב eruv stops being the loaf of bread, but
it means, you know, it starts being the actual walls themselves. Okay,
but what do you have to do in order to be able
to do the ערוב eruv and in order to enable to do
the loaf of bread? How do you do that for a רשות
הרבים? reshut harabim? עושה צורת הפתח מכאן ולחי וקורה מכאן. Oseh tzurat
hapetach mikan v'lechi v'korah mikan. So what you have to do is
you have to make a
צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, a doorframe on one side, and a לחי
וקורה lechi v'korah on the other side. Now where does the רשות
הרבים reshut harabim get its walls from? Right, if you're all you're
doing is a לחי lechi or קורה korah here and it's צורת
הפתח tzurat hapetach here, what about the other two walls? How does
that work, right? This is the whole point of רשות הרבים reshut
harabim is that it's basically unwalled around all sides. So רש״י Rashi
says what we're talking about is a case that you have, let's
say, you know those pictures in the, the mosaic in the Cardo
about ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it's got a wall around it and it has
this whole street straight through it, what was the name of the
street? The via something. Via Dolorosa?
No, but that's a different street.
Anyway, so
everybody knows the mosaic I'm talking about, right? Everybody's seen this mosaic?
Anyway. So basically, you've got a major thoroughfare that feeds in and
out of the city gates. Okay, here's the, whatever, city gates. So
now it's surrounded by two walls. It's surrounded by this wall and
this wall. But that's walls of two sides. It doesn't have walls
at these two openings. So to create at the actual place where
it leaves the city, to create a wall, one you need a
לחי lechi or קורה korah here and a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
here. Now you'll usually have something because now Because you'll have a
gate and that'll be a צורת הפתח. Tzurat Hapetach. But that's what
you would need. Now before we go on, a
צורת הפתח Tzurat Hapetach to get in and out of them would
be fine.
Yeah, yeah, a צורת הפתח Tzurat Hapetach is always better than a
לחי Lechi or קורה. Korah. לחי Lechi or קורה Korah is only
a partial צורת הפתח. Tzurat Hapetach. Now I have to say something
before we continue about defining רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. If you take
a look at רש"י, Rashi, רשות
הרבים, Reshus Harabim, it is about eight lines down in the wide
lines at the end of the line. So רש"י Rashi says: רשות
הרבים, Reshus Harabim, משמע רוחב שש עשרה אמה—it's mashma rochav sheish esrei
ama 16 amot wide—ועיר שמצוין בה שישים ריבוא. ve-ir she-metzuyin bah shishim
ribo. Okay, and a city that has 600,000 people. And every single
רש"י Rashi on this page, every time it says רשות הרבים, Reshus
Harabim, רש"י Rashi says, and there were 600,000 people, 600,000 people, 600,000
people. Never in the גמרא. Gemara. Take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
כיצד מערבין דרך רשות הרבים, keitzad me-arvin derech reshus harabim, right, תוספות
Tosafot about six lines from the bottom says: פירוש הקונטרס רשות הרבים
רוחב י"ו אמה ומפולש משני
צדדים—open peirush hakuntres reshus harabim rochav yud vav ama u-mefulash mi-shnei tzedadim
at both ends—משער לשער—from misha'ar lisha'ar gate to gate—ומצוין בה שישים ריבוא,
u-metzuyin bah shishim ribo, and there's 600,000. וכן יש בהלכות גדולות דבעינן
דריסת שישים ריבוא, ve-chein yeish be-halachos gedolos de-ba'inan drisas shishim ribo, and
that's also in the בה"ג Bahag and the גאונים. Geonim.
So the גאונים Geonim introduce a criteria of 600,000 people. And what
that does is, is allow already in the time of the ראשונים
Rishonim for them to say that nowadays we don't have רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabim. We don't have cities that have 600,000 people that use
it—I know—use it for this side. And therefore all of the problems
we're about to encounter about the difficulty of making an עירוב Eiruv
in a רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, you know, making the walls around
a רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, they basically say, well that doesn't apply
to us because we don't have a real רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim.
Of course the key criteria, 600,000, isn't in the גמרא, Gemara, but
it gets introduced at the time of the גאונים. Geonim. And that's
the major debate nowadays around עירובין. Eiruvin. There are two debates. One
is, do you in principle even think it's possible? Because if you
say you don't need 600,000 people, then you have רשות הרבים. Reshus
Harabim. And if you have a real רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, we're
going to find out that you can't really, you know, unless you
really have walls, you can't really get started. Okay. So the only
possibility of an עירוב Eiruv is if you say we don't have
a real רשות הרבים, Reshus Harabim, which means you buy into this
600,000 criteria. And then there are debates even if you do that,
have you satisfied all of the criteria? Okay, but the first real
threshold you have to pass is this because what we're going to
find out is that if you have a real רשות הרבים, Reshus
Harabim, it's pretty impossible to make it into a רשות היחיד. Reshus
Hayachid. So by adding this criteria, it opens up the possibility that
we can have עירובין Eiruvin nowadays. Yeah.
The שישים ריבוא, shishim ribo, is that for a single passage sixteen
אמה ama wide? Right. So thank you for mentioning that.
So then it becomes a big debate even within the 600,000. Does
that mean 600,000 people use the street? Or does it mean the
600,000 people, the city has 600,000 people in it and it's sort
of usable by 600,000 people? If it means 600,000 people use the
street, does it mean on a daily basis? You know, how frequently?
It gets to the point where, you know, as Michael pointed out,
you know, that criteria doesn't even save you all the time nowadays
in a big city like Manhattan, right? I mean you have Broadway,
you know, there are 600,000 people that use Broadway.
I looked at traffic counts.
Really? So how many people...
we only know by
the number of cars, right? Cars.
But there might be more than one person per car.
They did that when they were building an עירוב Eiruv for Flatbush
with Topol, the BQE or something.
70 to 90
thousand cars is the biggest controversy whether it's more than 600,000.
It's clearly not the case, I looked at traffic counts.
Okay, but the West Side Highway or FDR might get it, no?
The busiest highway in the state of New York is the George
Washington Bridge which gets about 300,000 vehicles a day. Almost all of
them are single passenger. And the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway and the Verrazzano-Narrows Bridge
are a little bit below that. Wow. None of the streets that
people talk about like Ocean Parkway have even 100,000. Very interesting.
Okay. So if you say 600,000 a day, then and if those
numbers are correct, then that's, you know, obviously opens up the possibility.
But they go back and forth.
Which is the same car which means you divide by two. But
you could have two... but you go back and forth... most of
them are No,
they talk about 600,000 people, not 600,000 trips. But I do also
want to say, by the way, that when I heard this issue
and the claims were being made that it was used by 600,000
people,
a counter-argument was that the people actually weren't walking on the רשות
הרבים. Reshus Harabim. They were in their cars and they were higher
than ten טפחים tefachim off of the ground of the רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabim. Oh my God. Very... how would a closed car be
a רשות היחיד? Reshus Hayachid? Well, so
it was a similar type of an argument. Okay, anyway, so now
back to the גמרא. Gemara.
But תוספות Tosafot though, so he's saying that even without 600,000...
No, he raises the possibility maybe not. There is a מחלוקת ראשונים
machlokes Rishonim about whether you buy into that criteria. Yeah, if I
didn't make it clear, the גאונים Geonim introduced the criteria, there's a
מחלוקת machlokes in the ראשונים Rishonim whether to accept that as a
real
criteria. is the
most is the is the prevalent vehicle through which that in through
which that information gets just read into the גמרא, Gemara, but it
originates in the גאונים. Geonim. Okay, not the מדרש, Midrash, the גאונים.
Geonim. That's why he mentions that תוספות Tosafot quotes the הלכות גדולות.
Halachot Gedolot. I see. Okay. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: כיצד מערבין דרך
רשות הרבים? Keitzad me'arvin derech reshut harabbim?
Back to that. עושה צורת הפתח מכאן ולחי או קורה מכאן. Oseh
tzurat hapetach mikan velechi o korah mikan. So if you have a
רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabbim, here we find out maybe it's not so
hard, you know, if you've got walls on two sides and you
only have to do a לחי lechi or קורה korah on one
and a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach on the other side. Okay, not
so bad. You can do a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach מכאן. mikan.
חנניה אומר: Hananiah omer: but חנניה Hananiah disagrees. He says, בית שמאי
אומרים: Beit Shammai omerim:
it's a debate of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל. Beit
Hillel. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says עושה דלת מכאן ודלת מכאן, oseh
delet mikan v'delet mikan, you have to actually make doors on both
sides. Okay, so you know, and none of this major thoroughfare type
of, you know, none of this like cars passing, people walking straight
through. And not only do you have to make doors on both
sides, וכשהוא יוצא ונכנס נועל. u'keshehu yotze ve'nichnas no'el. When you go
in and out you have to close the door. So according to
בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, the only way this could be a רשות
היחיד Reshut HaYachid is if not only you had a gate, but
you had a closed gate that would only open when you need
to come in.
Which wouldn't have worked even in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Right. Okay,
so that's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai says. בית הלל אומרים: Beit
Hillel omerim: עושה דלת מכאן ולחי או קורה מכאן. oseh delet mikan
velechi o korah mikan. You need you can one side I admit
you can do a לחי lechi or קורה, korah, but the other
side you need a real door. Presumably you don't need to close
the door when you go in or out or he would have
said it. Okay. But at least you need a real door on
one side. רשות... Reshut... now the גמרא Gemara says: So that's one
that's the first bit. But now the גמרא Gemara makes it even
harder. רשות הרבים מי מיערבא? Reshut harabbim mi mi'arva? Since when do
you do an עירוב eruv in a רשות הרבים? reshut harabbim? Those
three words רשות הרבים מי מיערבא reshut harabbim mi mi'arva are like
key, right, because that means essentially that contains the idea if you
have a real רשות הרבים reshut harabbim you ain't gonna do an
עירוב. eruv. All right, and that's why all of the debates are:
do we have a real רשות הרבים reshut harabbim nowadays? Okay, so
if you ever the גמרא Gemara says: I don't get it, if
it's a real רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, since when can you make
the עירוב? eruv? והתניא: Ve'hatanya: יתר על כן אמר רבי יהודה: Yeter
al ken amar Rabbi Yehuda: רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said even more
than something else, which I'm not going to worry now what the
something else is, it's irrelevant for us, but let's see what he
did say. מי שהיו לו שני בתים משני צדי רשות הרבים. Mi
shehayu lo shene batim mishene tzidei reshut harabbim. Somebody had two houses
on the two sides of רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. עושה לחי מכאן
ולחי מכאן או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן ונושא ונותן באמצע. Oseh lechi
mikan velechi mikan o korah mikan vekorah mikan venoseh venoten ba'emtza. So
similar to our case, except instead of being in a walled city,
basically what you do is you've got your house here and you
know and your house here, here's your house, you have houses on
both sides of Broadway, you're very rich, okay,
and you want to you have two apartment buildings on both sides
of Broadway and you want to basically be able to carry from
one to the other, so what does he say? He says עושה
לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן או קורה מכאן וקורה מכאן, oseh lechi mikan
velechi mikan o korah mikan vekorah mikan, a לחי lechi here, a
לחי lechi here, and now you can this essentially acts as a
wall on both sides and now you can you know make Broadway,
that section of Broadway, into a רשות היחיד. Reshut HaYachid. Okay, that's
what חנניה... Hananiah... that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. It's very
radical. The גמרא Gemara will tell us soon that רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda holds that actually two walls might be sufficient דאורייתא. de'oraita. Two
walls already stop it from being a רשות הרבים reshut harabbim basically.
So that's what he says, you know, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says. Okay. עושה לחי מכאן ולחי מכאן או קורה מכאן וקורה
מכאן ונושא ונותן באמצע. Oseh lechi mikan velechi mikan o korah mikan
vekorah mikan venoseh venoten ba'emtza. And now you can carry in the
space in between. אמרו לו: Amru lo: the sages said back to
him, אין מערבין רשות הרבים בכך. En me'arvin reshut harabbim bechach. Excuse
me, that is not that is not sufficient to make an עירוב
eruv in a רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, just doing a לחי lechi
or a קורה korah on both sides of the ends of the
street. So the גמרא Gemara says: So you see you can't make
a רשות reshut an עירוב eruv in a רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
Now of course that's not such a good argument because they could
just say that's not enough, you need something more. וכי תימא: V'chi
tema: and you'll say בכך הוא דלא מיערבא, bechach hu de'lo me'arva,
that's not enough, הא בדלתות מיערבא, ha bidlatot me'arva, if you make
a door like the you know or צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach maybe
that would be okay. No. והאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן: Ve'ha'amar Rabbah bar Bar Hana amar Rabbi Yochanan: רבה בר בר
חנה Rabbah bar Bar Hana says in the name of רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, ירושלים, Yerushalayim, here's a nice practical example, אלמלא דלתותיה נעולות
בלילה, elmale dlatoteha ne'ulot balaila, were it
not that they would lock the gates of ירושלים Yerushalayim at night,
היו חייבין עליה משום רשות הרבים. hayavu aleha mishum reshut harabbim. Then
if you carried in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, presumably that's in the major street,
you would be transgressive even though it's a walled city. That the
walled city doesn't save you and the gates of the walled city
don't save you, it's only the fact that they have not only
do they have gates, but that the gates are locked for part
of the day, they're locked at night. So you see that if
you've got a major thoroughfare, it is not enough at both ends
to do something like a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach or a door,
you ממש mammish need a door that will even be locked for
part of the day. Okay, so this is the idea that the
point which is so key that a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
you're never going to make it unless you're dealing with a walled
city, you're never going to make an עירוב eruv because you can
have as many צורת הפתח tzuras hapesachs as you want, unless you
actually close off the street for part of the day with a
door, okay, you're not going to be able to make a רשות
היחיד, reshus hayachid, so you're not going to be able to make
an עירוב. eruv. So the question's going to be, how does that
fit with everything we've just said a minute ago, which is that
there are ways to make an עירוב eruv in a רשות הרבים?
reshus harabbim? So that's the גמרא's Gemara's question. So ואמר עולא, ve'amar
Ulla, let's just give another example: הני אבולי דמחוזא, hani abbulei deMechuza,
the gates of Mechuza, יומא דלית דלתותיהן ננעלות, yoma dleit daltoteihen ninalot,
if it were not that they were locked, that they would lock
their gates for certain times during the day, חייבין עליהם משום רשות
הרבים, chayavin aleihem mishum reshus harabbim, you'd be חייב. chayav. So again
you see it's not enough to have a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach
at the end. You really need to close it off. By the
way, just to show how רש"י Rashi consistently injects the 600,000, if
you look at רש"י Rashi אבולי דמחוזא, abbulei deMechuza, again about twelve
lines down in the narrow lines, רש"י Rashi says, שערי העיר, sha'arei
ha'ir, מכוונים זה כנגד זה mechuvannin zeh keneged zeh with straight through,
open end, והיו בה ששים ריבוא, vehayu bah shishim ribo, again 600,000.
So that's the רש"י Rashi for ירושלים Yerushalayim as well.
And he says it by ירושלים, Yerushalayim, constantly insisting that these were
cases of 600,000. Okay, so back to the גמרא. Gemara.
So again the question is, if it's a real רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, you need to close off the ends of the street for
part of the day. How did we say before that it would
work if you just had like a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach or
you had a door that even if you didn't close it? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב יהודה הכי קאמר, amar Rav Yehuda hachi ka'amar, here's how to
read that earlier ברייתא braita that gave you an easier way to
make an עירוב. eruv. כיצד מערבין, keitzad me'arvin, not real רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. Actually, this is a very interesting read of it. The
phrase was כיצד מערבין דרך רשות הרבים. keitzad me'arvin derech reshus harabbim.
What do you mean דרך רשות הרבים? derech reshus harabbim? Why didn't
it just say כיצד מערבין רשות הרבים? keitzad me'arvin reshus harabbim? So
he says what it means is not the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
the streets that feed into the רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. כיצד מערבין
מבואות המפולשים לרשות הרבים. keitzad me'arvin mavo'os hamefulashin lereshus harabbim. What do
you do not for the רשות reshus itself, but for the streets
that feed into it? That עושה צורת הפתח מכאן ולחי וקורה מכאן.
oseh tzuras hapesach mikan ulechi vekorah mikan. That is enough to make
a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach on one side or a לחי lechi
or קורה korah on the other. So again, here you have your
major thoroughfares and your cross streets. So if you want to get
a cross street, which is not the same degree of a major
thoroughfare, the reason it's a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim presumably is not
because it per se has the use that would define it as
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, but because it feeds into a רשות
הרבים. reshus harabbim. So it's easier therefore to make it permissible. So
you do a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach on one side as a
virtual wall and a לחי lechi or קורה korah on the other.
That cuts it off from the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and that
allows you to make that into an עירוב, eruv, because the צורת
הפתח tzuras hapesach counts as a real wall. And once you have
three real walls with the צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach, a לחי lechi
or קורה korah is enough. But for the major street, even if
you have like צורת הפתח's, tzuras hapesachs, it's not going to be
good because the reality is it's a major thoroughfare. And for the
major street, you basically need walls or closed doors or closed gates.
So now you see if you have a real רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, you're not going to ever make an עירוב eruv unless you're
in a walled city. Okay, but if you have something that's not
a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, what we learn from here is,
if it's not a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, what can function as
a wall? Because you only had two walls, but what functions as
the third? A צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. So when you have a
non-not real רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, you can make צורת הפתח's, tzuras
hapesachs, which is how we make our entire places acceptable through a
lot of צורת הפתח's. tzuras hapesachs. Okay, so this גמרא Gemara is
the key to basically explaining all the עירוב eruv wars. If you
have רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, no good unless you're in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
a walled city or נינווה Ninveh or something. Anyway, and if you
don't, you can use a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach.
So briefly, a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach would be what? I know
we didn't get
to it yet, but two sticks, ten טפחים tefachim high, and a
beam across them. What we basically do is we bang a stick
into the telephone pole directly under the telephone wires and we use
the telephone wires from one telephone pole to the next to be
the crossbeam. Reason we don't use the telephone poles themselves is because
the thing has to be directly above. And by telephone poles, the
way they're most- mostly the way they're constructed is that the wires
are off to the side, they're not directly on top of the
beam part of the pole.
That's too high, right?
No, they're not too high. We use the wires. We just have
to bang in another beam directly underneath them.
So the beam doesn't have to be attached to the pole?
Right, it just has to be directly under, yeah.
I just looked up the traffic count, the pedestrian count for Times
Square. Yes,
370,000 in December.
Wow, okay, so there you go, so 600,000 saves.
And it is- and Times-
in the whole month?
In the whole month, okay, an- on an average day? On the
average day. And Times Square is not in the עירוב eruv right
now.
Ah, interesting. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, איתמר. itamar.
Okay, so now we know, unless you got walls, you can't make
a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. But what you can do if
it’s even a side street feeding in and it’s as once it’s
not the primary רשות הרבים reshus harabbim then the צורת הפתח tzurah
hapesach helps you. איתמר. Itmar. רב אמר הלכה כתנא קמא. Rav amar
halacha ketanna kamma.
Now within this issue about the what we have now said means
is the case of the side streets, the מבואות המפולשות, mevo’os hamefulashos,
רב Rav says we rule like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, which
is even more lenient, which is a לחי lechi or קורה korah
on both sides, which is very lenient. ושמואל אמר הלכה כחנניה. U’shmuel
amar halacha ke-Chananya. We rule like חנניה Chananya who said it’s a
debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel and
according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, at least one of the sides
needs a צורת הפתח. tzurah hapesach. So איבעיא להו. ibaya lehu. They
asked. לחנניה אליבא דבית הלל, Le-Chananya aliba de-Beis Hillel, for חנניה Chananya
according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, that one of the sides excuse
me, בית הלל Beis Hillel did not say צורת הפתח, tzurah hapesach,
בית הלל Beis Hillel actually said one of the sides you need
a door, right? I'm sorry I'm sorry חנניה Chananya said, I misstated
it. I'm sorry. חנניה, Chananya, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said what
I've been saying, which is צורת הפתח tzurah hapesach on one side
and a לחי lechi on the other. That's what I've been telling
you. That's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. That's what רב Rav says
and that's how we do rule. And שמואל Shmuel does more and
more. בית הלל Beis Hillel according to חנניה, Chananya, which says a
צורת הפתח tzurah hapesach is not enough, you actually need a door.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu,
they asked the question. לחנניה אליבא דבית הלל, Le-Chananya aliba de-Beis Hillel,
for חנניה Chananya according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, צריך לנעול או
אין צריך לנעול? tzarich lin'ol o ein tzarich lin'ol? We said you
needed a door at one end, a צורת הפתח tzurah hapesach is
not enough. You have to lock it or not, close it or
not? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, you need not the
entire time but for part of the time like we've seen. תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, D'amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, אינו צריך לנעול. eino tzarich lin'ol. According to
that בית הלל Beis Hillel you don't have to close it. But
maybe it means you don't have to open and close it every
time you go in and out. וכן אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל,
Vechain amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, אינו צריך לנעול. eino tzarich lin'ol.
Similarly another statement in the name of שמואל Shmuel you do not
have to close it. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amrei, some say. אמר רב
מתנא בדידי הוה עובדא, Amar Rav Masna bedidi hava uvda, I actually
had a case just like this about this side street, ואמר לי
שמואל, ve'amar li Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel said to me, אין צריך
לנעול, ein tzarich lin'ol, you don't have to close it. Which by
the way all of this discussion indicates that they are all following
this פסק psak that you do need a door, you just don't
have to close it, which would make our life a lot more
difficult. Okay, but we actually rule like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
which is you don't need a door and all you need is
a צורת הפתח. tzurah hapesach. Okay, but here at least
but anyway by the way our scenarios could be even better than
this because this is not just a non-רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, I
mean this is actually a thing that is connected to a real
רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim.
And when it’s and
when it’s connected it actually has a status of a רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. So if you say we don't have any real רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim we might even be better than that case because
this case is more problematic because it involves deals with the presence
of a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. Okay, but within that case even
dealing with רשות הרבים reshus harabbim there's a debate about whether for
the third wall you need a צורת הפתח tzurah hapesach or do
you need a door? And assuming you need a door according to
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, do you have to close it or not?
And here the גמרא Gemara saying you do not have to close
it, אין צריך לנעול. ein tzarich lin'ol. Now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. בעו מיניה מרב ענן. Be’u minei me-Rav Anan. So they
asked the same question from רב ענן. Rav Anan. צריך לנעול או
אין צריך לנעול? Tzarich lin’ol o ein tzarich lin’ol? Do you have
to close it or not? אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said. תו
חזו, Tu chazu, come and see. הני אבולי דנהרדעא, Hanei abuli de-Neharde’a,
the gates of
נהרדעא, Neharde’a, דטימון עד פלגייהו בעפרא, de-timun ad palgeihu be-afra, that up
to half of them were sort of stopped up with dirt, meaning
and the gates could not close. So you see and it still
was okay to carry. So you see you don't have to close
the gates because those gates couldn't
close. So והוה עייל ונפיק מר שמואל, ve-hava ayyil ve-nafik Mar Shmuel,
and again all of this is testimony in the name of שמואל.
Shmuel. And שמואל Shmuel would carry in those streets, people would carry
in those
streets. No. והוה עייל ונפיק מר
שמואל, Ve-hava ayyil ve-nafik Mar Shmuel, and מר שמואל Mar Shmuel would
go in and out, ולא אמר להו ולא מידי, ve-lo amar lehu
ve-lo midi, and he would not tell them anything meaning he would
not he would not stop them from carrying in the street. So
אמר רב כהנא, amar Rav Kahana, so you see that the doors
don't have to don't have to be closed. So רב כהנא Rav
Kahana said, no. הנך מגופות
הוו. Hanach megupos havay. True that there was dirt there that stopped
them up and they weren't able to fully close, but they were
partially closed. So you can't prove anything from that. Maybe that would
be enough to be considered closed. So you can't prove from there
that you do not need them to be closed. Now I should
say something by the way that since it says the gates of
מחוזא, Mechuza, it makes it sound like it is the main thoroughfare
of the street, right? But we have just we have just said
that all this discussion is only by the side streets. רש״י Rashi
says we have to be talking about a case where there’s gates
of one street feeding into a side street. You sort of have
them like in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? You have a lot of streets
that have gates you know sort of by them as well. But
the gates with doors? Like gated communities, I guess you could imagine.
But again we are talking here that according to the way the
גמרא Gemara explains it we’re talking here about side streets. Okay, so
we still have this question which is when you are allowed to
do this thing for a third wall and if you need a
door according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, does it have to be
something that will be closed or not?
Did בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say both gates need to be
closed or something like that?
Yeah, he said that.
No, he said he said you know he
said you have to open and close it as you’re going in
and out. Yeah, yeah. כי אתא רב נחמן אמר, Ki asa Rav
Nachman amar, when רב נחמן Rav Nachman came he said, פניו לעפריה,
panyu l’afreih, that
that they removed the dirt. Okay, that it was not acceptable to
have the dirt stopping it up. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא
קסבר רב נחמן צריך לנעול? leima kasavar Rav Nachman tzarich lin'ol?
Maybe from this we can infer that רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
that these have to be closed? It says לא, lo, no, כיון
דראויה לינעל אף על פי שאינה. keivan derauya linnael af al pi
she-eina. Right,
as long as they're able to be closed, they don't have to
actually be closed. Okay, so again to take a step back and
review what we've said. If you have a real רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, you need it to really have the openings and exit ממש
mamash closed off with doors for part of the day. If you
have a side street, מבואות מפולשין לרשות הרבים, mavo-os mefulashin l'reshus harabbim,
so there what do you need for the third wall? One wall
could be a לחי lechi or קורה. kora. What do you need
for the third wall? Either a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach or you
need a door.
Within the idea of the door, we said you don't have to
close it but you might have to be able to close it.
Okay, so all of this again I know maybe sounds, you know,
complicated which it probably is. But it's highly relevant because the first
part means that if you have a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
unless you're in a walled city you can't make an עירוב eruv
because nobody is closing off streets every day. And the second part
means that when you don't have a real רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim,
צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach might suffice. And even the discussion in the
גמרא Gemara that you might need a door and maybe it has
to be able to be closed or whatever could be because we're
dealing with streets that feed into a רשות הרבים. reshus harabbim. But
when they don't feed into, you know, then it could be everybody
could agree that a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach will suffice. Okay, so
now... yes?
One
of the operative features how we can make an עירוב eruv with
Henry Hudson Parkway going down the middle? What?
One more time.
We've got the parkway going right down the middle of the
street.
Yeah, but that's what I'm saying. Basically the operative features are exactly.
Exactly. You have the parkways, you
have all these things. If you don't call it a רשות הרבים,
reshus harabbim, then a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach could be enough, right?
And there's no issue of the control of the traffic flow.
Controlling the traffic flow is what the גמרא Gemara is discussing about
doors and closing the doors and the ability to close the doors,
that is about controlling the traffic flow.
But we don't do that.
We say צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach suffices. That's exactly the difference between
the צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach position and the door position. צורת הפתח
tzuras hapesach is a, could be a complete virtual wall, not only
invisible but porous, you know, complete, fully imaginary wall. Okay, and that's
the way we rule. The other position is that you need a
door, which means at least, you know, conceptually or maybe even in
practice the ability to control the traffic flow. Again, in the גמרא
Gemara they're discussing it by streets that feed into a רשות הרבים.
reshus harabbim. If you claim you don't have a רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim at all, could make things easier. Yeah?
When they built the עירוב eruv on the Upper West Side of
Manhattan, they actually built doors
so that they could close off so that even though they only
did it once a year about 3 a.m., they actually built doors
where they would seal off the streets in the entire neighborhood once
a year.
Where did they build the doors?
They built these contraptions, we saw them at the עירובין Eruvin exhibit
at the Center for Jewish History. They had these fabric things they
would pull out to create a door once a year. Block it.
What street? What street? Central Park West, 106th.
The city let them do that?
The city apparently Mayor Koch pulled rank on the Parks Department and
the Transportation Department.
And that structure is there the whole year?
And it's there the whole year
and once a year they actually pull something and close it.
I don't know if they still do. I don't know if they
still do, but they did.
There you go, a direct application of our גמרא. Gemara. Okay, to
be continued tomorrow.